<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Essays on CAUSES &amp; EFFECTS</title>
    <link>https://www.jamescampbell.us/categories/essays/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Essays on CAUSES &amp; EFFECTS</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-US</language>
    <copyright>All rights reserved © 2015-2019</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Tue, 04 Feb 2014 10:10:10 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="https://www.jamescampbell.us/categories/essays/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    <item>
      <title>On Photography and Joy</title>
      <link>https://www.jamescampbell.us/post/on-photography-and-joy/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 04 Feb 2014 10:10:10 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.jamescampbell.us/post/on-photography-and-joy/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;To Begin, What Do I Call Myself Online?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The problem with doing many things is that I have trouble filling in my bio information on social networking sites. Do I say &amp;lsquo;photographer&amp;rsquo; even though it is not my day job? Do I say &amp;lsquo;web developer&amp;rsquo; even though a lot of the times I am just solving issues for clients and not actually coding? Do I say founder of InstantDC.com and curator of photo exhibitions, even though this is usually once or twice a year? Do I say musician and one-man-band GoldForLions, with singles on iTunes even though I have made about $11 total from all of my efforts? Do I try to say something clever in my profile and avoid the issue of labels altogether?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There is no easy solution, but at 32 years old, I know myself and what I love to do. I love my wife and my four-month-old son. I love to tinker with things, I love to solve problems in creative ways (strange phrase - as opposed to non-creative ways?). I love to create art with technology and showcase technology with art. I love playing guitar and creating music. I enjoy the instant gratification of changing a stylesheet and seeing a webpage change when I hit Command+R.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Maybe the guide to what drives me is this simple statement: what brings me joy is also what challenges me. And also: what brings me joy allows me to challenge myself.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Was I excited about having the opportunity to manage a photo exhibit at FotoweekDC last year? Yes. Did it turn out exactly the way I planned? No. But I am glad I did it because it was very challenging to manage 12 different photography groups and volunteers for an entire week. I learned a lot about what works and what doesn&amp;rsquo;t work when putting on a large-scale photography exhibition.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Every time I push myself to do something new, I learn new things, meet new people, and gain perspective. This is a positive feedback loop that I use to gain confidence in each new endeavor.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Photography and Developing Your Visual Language&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Bear with me as I try to explain what is very hard to put into words: the experience of taking and viewing a photograph.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Photography is an amalgamation of technology, art, and magic. I am eager to go where it takes me. There is always something strange to see around the next corner. Even that same corner at a different time of day or season can be another planet. Every time my eye finds the viewfinder, that rectangular scene is looking back at me. Sometimes the scene mocks me. Sometimes it beckons me. Sometimes it is laughing in the dust. Becoming better at the craft of photography is building a working relationship with what is through the looking-glass.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our visual intelligence is being trained over time into a new vocabulary made up of colors, shapes, and light. This visual language is pictographic and temporal. A blue square of chipped paint and an organic green pine tree are connected via a gray sky and crooked sidewalk. But tomorrow the chipped paint is fixed, the pine tree is cut, and the sky is now blue. The sidewalk is also fixed. Did the scene change or did the viewer&amp;rsquo;s perspective in time?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To go further into the challenges of viewing a photo, sometimes a word destroys an entire photographic experience. I stopped titling my photos because I was framing too much for the viewer. If I titled something &amp;ldquo;Wall on 30th Street&amp;rdquo; you would be prepared for a wall, but maybe without the title you would have interpreted the scene as a very flat puppy? I stopped writing captions for the same reasons. Words ruin photographs. I am a firm believer in training yourself to see over time in your own way and to avoid words at all costs. My favorite photographers are the ones who are taciturn as they go about their craft. This does not necessarily require them to be introverted, but when they are in the mode of taking photographs, they are creating and cultivating a louder silence.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As you build up your visual vocabulary, you will recognize in other&amp;rsquo;s photographs attempts to solve similar riddles. Patterns develop overtime as one photographer is influenced by another and you will see how genres of street photos, portrait, and landscape photos evolve. Each decision you make with a photograph does not need explanation. The viewer will either understand or not, or interpret it differently based on their own experiences and own personal vocabularies that they have build up over time according to their place and experience in their own societal bubble.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is one of the best things about our new picture-taking culture. The societal bubbles are popping. The internet allows you to self-select and curate, but it also allows you to discover something new. It is true that we are being over-saturated with millions of images per day. This, to me, sounds like a problem of lack of curation, something that technology may help solve. The positives to this drowning in images is that we are all building up a strong visual intelligence as both observer and creators of images as we sink slowly to the bottom of this sweet abyss.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;So, to get to whether or not to call myself a photographer.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Whew, that was long-winded but I am leaving it as is. Onward:
I waffle back and forth between stating that I am a photographer in my profiles. The issue here is what it means to be a photographer. Here is how I define it:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For me, photography is a need. It is a requirement for happiness. It is searching for visual puzzles to solve. It is pushing the mind to the edges of what reality can be into a super-reality of shapes, colors, light and dark. It is the shocking feeling of the banal. It is the juxtaposition of what we have done to the world and what the world has done to us. It is the opportunity to stop time. It is my passion and my art and it continues to surprise me. I define a successful photograph on my own terms and I am my own harshest critic.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My four month old son and my wife bring me so much happiness and have changed me in so many ways I cannot express it in words, but at my core being I still have this need to create things and this will never go away. It is who I am, it is part of my being. It goes beyond ambition, greed, etc. With less free time nowadays, I rely on photography even more to fill this need and I cannot wait to see where this desire takes me next.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thank you for reading and attempting to understand why I call myself a photographer.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>2013 The Year We Missed</title>
      <link>https://www.jamescampbell.us/post/The-Year-We-Missed/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 31 Dec 2013 04:10:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.jamescampbell.us/post/The-Year-We-Missed/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;p&gt;In 2013, we looked pretty ridiculous standing around staring at our phones, tablets, phablets, and iPads.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My goal in this post is to share photos I have curated that document the phenomenon of humans interacting with new technology.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Since I believe I am a better curator than writer, I will try to keep the words to a minimum.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;http://farm8.staticflickr.com/7238/7049846391_fd4cc6cb7c_b_d.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;man on phone&#34; /&gt;
&lt;p class=&#34;pcaption&#34;&gt;photo credit Timothy Kraus&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div&gt;&lt;img class=&#39;protected&#39; src=&#34;http://farm9.staticflickr.com/8527/8498642548_dc4a26274a_b_d.jpg&#34;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;pcaption&#34;&gt;photo credit Adam Toms&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div&gt;&lt;img class=&#39;protected&#39; src=&#34;http://farm4.staticflickr.com/3834/10597478216_ced90d393e_b_d.jpg&#34;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;pcaption&#34;&gt;photo credit Steve Baker&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div&gt;&lt;img class=&#39;protected&#39; src=&#34;http://farm6.staticflickr.com/5484/9281447839_b4313457e2_b_d.jpg&#34; &gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;pcaption&#34;&gt;photo credit Sally Walton&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;New technology is great, but we need to figure out what it means and how it fits into our lives.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Were our lives more meaningful and rich when we were analog?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What can we do today to enable meaning in a world that expresses emotion through a like button?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div&gt;&lt;img class=&#39;protected&#39; src=&#34;http://farm4.staticflickr.com/3607/3564918558_7605a5930a_b_d.jpg&#34; width=&#34;640&#34;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;pcaption&#34;&gt;photo credit Ed Yourdon&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The rise of hipster culture is an indication of our collective nostalgia for what we did before the cloud came along that digitized, monetized, and made available everything we want at a moments notice.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My wife and I have a rule: &lt;em&gt;no phones out at meals&lt;/em&gt;. It is simple, but it really works. What other rules make sense?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div&gt;&lt;img class=&#39;protected&#39; src=&#34;http://farm4.staticflickr.com/3154/2380627237_6a669f9314_b_d.jpg&#34; width=&#34;640&#34;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;pcaption&#34;&gt;photo credit Oren Levine&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div&gt;&lt;img class=&#39;protected&#39; src=&#34;http://farm9.staticflickr.com/8093/8413870690_0390f59a2d_b_d.jpg&#34; width=&#34;640&#34;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;pcaption&#34;&gt;photo credit Stefano Mirabella&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div&gt;&lt;img class=&#39;protected&#39; src=&#34;http://farm4.staticflickr.com/3500/3754271881_2f1436cf13_b_d.jpg&#34; width=&#34;480&#34;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;pcaption&#34;&gt;photo credit Oren Levine&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;2014-is-the-year-we-will-start-to-figure-it-out:b0ff82f7954f4046a2465a5e1b65d296&#34;&gt;2014 is the year we will start to figure it out.&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;2014 is the year we start finding smart uses for our technology that enable human connection, interaction, and sharing, as opposed to keeping us apart even when we are in the same room.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;happy-new-year:b0ff82f7954f4046a2465a5e1b65d296&#34;&gt;Happy New Year!&lt;/h2&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Mobile Photographers Make Great Salesmen</title>
      <link>https://www.jamescampbell.us/post/Mobile-Photographers-Make-Great-Salesmen/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 11 Sep 2012 15:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.jamescampbell.us/post/Mobile-Photographers-Make-Great-Salesmen/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;For 3 months when I was 19 years old, I worked as a car salesman. I was probably one of the worst in Pennsylvania, if not the entire United States. I was one of three hires, and I didn’t know it then but the dealership was only going to keep one of us. This was all by design.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I naively thought that it would be easy, and that people would just say yes to me because I was a likeable guy. I offered everything to my customers, I threw in extras that my bosses would never agree to, losing many sales in the process. I over-sold the deal. When they let me go, I learned a valuable lesson: under-promise and over-deliver.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The best way to make your clients happy is to follow this philosophy. For example, if you think a project will take a week, double the time period. Then when you finish early, everyone wins.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So getting back to the title of this post, in my mind, this is what mobile photography has become, a giant game of lowering expectations to deliver something better than expected.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I will try to explain:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When you visit a person’s exhibit (virtual or otherwise) who claims to be an ‘iphoneographer’ or ‘mobile photographer’, your expectations are lowered. After all, how good could photographs be from a mobile device? Thus, in your mind, the trap is set, the bar is lowered and you are ready to be dazzled. When you see the inevitable array of decent photographs, you will exclaim ‘Wow! I can’t believe these were taken with a mobile phone. These are really great, for an iPhone!”. The artist will feel good about the praise, but you probably won’t buy any of their works, because you realize what has happened and you can’t really take them seriously because you are thinking to yourself, ‘hmmm, I can probably do the same thing with my phone…’. ​&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you are seriously trying to be an artist, be careful with the labels you choose. You may be setting the bar too low, and that ‘jaw drop’ effect will be far too easy to achieve. As an alternative, you can try setting the bar higher and really challenge yourself and your audience. Try not even labeling your works at all. Try focusing merely on the composition, the work itself. If you can achieve that same ‘WOW’ and ‘jaw-drop’ effect without the qualifier ‘for a mobile phone’ or ‘for a digital painting’ or ‘for an animated gif’ or any of the other phrases that qualify and undermine your creations, then you really have succeeded as an artist showcasing your art.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It should not be about the tool used, this is logically self-evident. So why would you choose to label yourself and associate yourself with the tool you use? If I take photos with only Nikon equipment, am I a Nikonographer? Or DSLRographer? Or filmographer? You can see how ridiculous this sounds. Unless I was sponsored by Nikon, I would never ever consider this as a proper label. Labels and logical taxonomies are only useful for specific instances, like contests and juried exhibitions, where the stakeholders want an even playing field and the sponsors want to push their products to the proper audience. The limitations that are set for certain exhibitions even help artists use their creativity within the constraints. This is all well and good, but outside of these specific instances, why would you constrain yourself and reduce your work to a specific category?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Of course, I am expecting this to be misread as an affront to mobile photography, but I assure you, that was not my intent, I am only trying to communicate a complicated concept that has been floating around in my head, and this is hard to distill in a way that is easily understood by all.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When I travel back to PA, I smile when I pass the old dealership, long since shutdown and left dilapidated on the side of the highway. I feel like somehow even though it was terrible at the time to be let go, if I would have stayed on as a car salesman at that place that would have been my fate.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>