<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Writing on CAUSES &amp; EFFECTS</title>
    <link>https://jamescampbell.us/tags/writing/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Writing on CAUSES &amp; EFFECTS</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-US</language>
    <copyright>All rights reserved © 2015-2019</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Wed, 31 Oct 2012 15:00:00 -0500</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="https://jamescampbell.us/tags/writing/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    <item>
      <title>Creative Existence In The Digital Age</title>
      <link>https://jamescampbell.us/post/creative-existence-in-the-digital-age/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 31 Oct 2012 15:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://jamescampbell.us/post/creative-existence-in-the-digital-age/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;My best works will never be shared on Facebook. They will never be tweeted and retweeted by the robotic hoard. They will never show up in the ever-growing free places to post digital works in exchange for digital ad space.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Yes indeed, I feel more and more like unsharing. I also feel the need to dislike things I stumble upon while browsing the vast digital art landscape, but there is no dislike button. There is only &amp;lsquo;like&amp;rsquo; or silence. And my Internet silence is not golden. It is a brooding decaying wasteland of &amp;ldquo;look at me&amp;rdquo; and &amp;ldquo;please follow me&amp;rdquo; and &amp;ldquo;buy me.&amp;rdquo; It is a sick place where society shows off it&amp;rsquo;s twisted consumptive low-brow half-baked underbelly.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I want no part of it. But I cannot look away from kittens. Also, friends were wondering why I didn&amp;rsquo;t have a Facebook account.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I would shut everything down if I could, but I realize this digital escapism, however noble it seems on its face, is doomed to failure much like the escapism of the last century. People packed up their RV&amp;rsquo;s, ran to their cabins in the woods, grew their own food, but when the illusion was over they still had to slog back to work after the holiday weekend to make money to live, and in turn perpetuate the holy lie for another generation. I am still slogging through this Internet wasteland hoping for the tiny glimpses of humanity I find from time to time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But is this the golden future we were promised on the backs of the last century? Technology without humanity? Sleek Aluminium &amp;amp; glass without emotion? Multi-touch without human-touch? Self-affirmation and a voice on a personal blog but no longer a real connection to society? Snarky clever commentary behind a firewall of avatars instead of real discussion?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So what should I do with my creations? I will send the most mundane of them to be consumed by the unnamable digitalis and I will keep my best works for myself, for my co-conspirators, cohorts, gallery representatives, limited edition books, friends, and family. I will post these works on my own walls of my own home with my own hands and remain human and true to myself. I will share a few of these things on my own site that I created on a server I coded myself. In this way, I will never lose my muse, and I will be free to do as I please. All the while I hold out hope for a dislike button.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The ironic thing is you will probably post this on Facebook and share it with all your internet friends. And then LOLCATZ will be the only suitable response.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Mobile Photographers Make Great Salesmen</title>
      <link>https://jamescampbell.us/post/Mobile-Photographers-Make-Great-Salesmen/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 11 Sep 2012 15:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://jamescampbell.us/post/Mobile-Photographers-Make-Great-Salesmen/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;For 3 months when I was 19 years old, I worked as a car salesman. I was probably one of the worst in Pennsylvania, if not the entire United States. I was one of three hires, and I didn’t know it then but the dealership was only going to keep one of us. This was all by design.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I naively thought that it would be easy, and that people would just say yes to me because I was a likeable guy. I offered everything to my customers, I threw in extras that my bosses would never agree to, losing many sales in the process. I over-sold the deal. When they let me go, I learned a valuable lesson: under-promise and over-deliver.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The best way to make your clients happy is to follow this philosophy. For example, if you think a project will take a week, double the time period. Then when you finish early, everyone wins.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So getting back to the title of this post, in my mind, this is what mobile photography has become, a giant game of lowering expectations to deliver something better than expected.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I will try to explain:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When you visit a person’s exhibit (virtual or otherwise) who claims to be an ‘iphoneographer’ or ‘mobile photographer’, your expectations are lowered. After all, how good could photographs be from a mobile device? Thus, in your mind, the trap is set, the bar is lowered and you are ready to be dazzled. When you see the inevitable array of decent photographs, you will exclaim ‘Wow! I can’t believe these were taken with a mobile phone. These are really great, for an iPhone!”. The artist will feel good about the praise, but you probably won’t buy any of their works, because you realize what has happened and you can’t really take them seriously because you are thinking to yourself, ‘hmmm, I can probably do the same thing with my phone…’. ​&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you are seriously trying to be an artist, be careful with the labels you choose. You may be setting the bar too low, and that ‘jaw drop’ effect will be far too easy to achieve. As an alternative, you can try setting the bar higher and really challenge yourself and your audience. Try not even labeling your works at all. Try focusing merely on the composition, the work itself. If you can achieve that same ‘WOW’ and ‘jaw-drop’ effect without the qualifier ‘for a mobile phone’ or ‘for a digital painting’ or ‘for an animated gif’ or any of the other phrases that qualify and undermine your creations, then you really have succeeded as an artist showcasing your art.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It should not be about the tool used, this is logically self-evident. So why would you choose to label yourself and associate yourself with the tool you use? If I take photos with only Nikon equipment, am I a Nikonographer? Or DSLRographer? Or filmographer? You can see how ridiculous this sounds. Unless I was sponsored by Nikon, I would never ever consider this as a proper label. Labels and logical taxonomies are only useful for specific instances, like contests and juried exhibitions, where the stakeholders want an even playing field and the sponsors want to push their products to the proper audience. The limitations that are set for certain exhibitions even help artists use their creativity within the constraints. This is all well and good, but outside of these specific instances, why would you constrain yourself and reduce your work to a specific category?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Of course, I am expecting this to be misread as an affront to mobile photography, but I assure you, that was not my intent, I am only trying to communicate a complicated concept that has been floating around in my head, and this is hard to distill in a way that is easily understood by all.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When I travel back to PA, I smile when I pass the old dealership, long since shutdown and left dilapidated on the side of the highway. I feel like somehow even though it was terrible at the time to be let go, if I would have stayed on as a car salesman at that place that would have been my fate.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The Goal</title>
      <link>https://jamescampbell.us/post/the-goal/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 01 Jul 2012 18:53:17 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://jamescampbell.us/post/the-goal/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;The goal should be do create things that make you happy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Destroy and otherwise ignore the things that don&amp;rsquo;t.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Never stop noticing the small things.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Never be too busy to be able to talk to a stranger about nothing.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>